Was that meant to be a barricade?
To ma być barykada?
You've only cut off your escape route.
Tylko odciąłeś sobie drogę ucieczki.
Just give up!
Poddaj się!
Without total control over that body, you cannot win.
Nie masz pełnej kontroli nad ciałem, więc przegrasz.
AUTHOR: HITOSHI IWAAKI
AUTOR: HITOSHI IWAAKI
Aside from your right hand,
Poza twoją prawą ręką
your entire body is useless, terrified of any pain.
całe ciało jest bezużyteczne, boi się bólu.
Huh?
Co?
If you become flustered and hold me back,
Jeśli się przestraszysz i mnie powstrzymasz,
we will lose.
przegramy.
Flustered?
Przestraszę?
Is he trying to get me flustered?
On chce mnie przestraszyć?
Migi.
Migi.
No, I can't just stay scared.
Nie mogę się bać.
They're so fast, I can't see anything.
Są szybcy, nic nie widzę.
Can I really do this?
Naprawdę dam radę?
We delegate roles.
Podzielimy się rolami.
I'll pretend to attack, but I'll focus on defense.
Wolę atakować, ale skupię się na obronie.
That'll make my defense practically impenetrable.
Nie przebije się przez moją obronę.
Then, who's going to attack?
A kto będzie atakował?
That'll have to be you, of course.
To jasne, że ty.
Me?
Ja?
What A's actions thus far have told me
Obserwowałem X i wiem,
is that he underestimates human ability.
że nie docenia ludzkich możliwości.
A will be cautious toward me,
Będzie uważał na mnie,
but he most likely will not have factored in your abilities at all.
ale pewnie nie przeanalizował twoich zdolności.
That is our advantage.
To nasza przewaga.
I will be defense and you will be offense.
Ja bronię, ty atakujesz.
That is the most effective delegation of roles.
To najlepszy podział ról.
Slowly approach him.
Powoli do niego podejdź.
Slowly, as if I'm being dragged toward him by Migi.
Powoli, jakby ciągnął mnie tam Migi.
Trust Migi.
Zaufaj Migiemu.
His defense is impeccable.
Nie przebiję się przez jego obronę.
That's right, Shinichi.
Właśnie, Shinichi.
What we can do that A cannot is division of labor.
My możemy podzielić się zadaniami, on nie.
It's just like Migi said.
Migi miał rację.
A doesn't think I'm capable of doing anything.
X myśli, że nic nie mogę zrobić.
All right!
Dobra!
I'm going to do this.
Zrobię to.
But he's still human from the neck down, right?
Od szyi w dół jest człowiekiem, prawda?
It's either him or us.
Albo on, albo my.
What is this pipe?
Co to za rura?
A table leg?
Noga od stołu?
We did it.
Udało nam się.
That much blood means it's fatal.
Traci dużo krwi, czyli umrze.
Impossible.
Niemożliwe.
The weak, cowardly human attacked?
Ten słaby, tchórzliwy człowiek zaatakował?
Wait.
Czekaj.
Let's see what he'll do.
Zobaczmy, co zrobi.
He seems to be in turmoil.
Chyba cierpi.
He got an artery close to the heart.
Trafił w tętnicę blisko serca. Muszę zatamować krwawienie.
I see.
Już rozumiem.
Pushing the pipe through his back gets rid of the "spout".
Wypchnął rurę przez plecy i zatamował krwotok.
All right.
Dobrze.
Go after him.
Bierz go.
Let's finish him.
Zabijmy go.
No!
Nie!
I've had enough!
Mam dość!
But we shouldn't leave him like that.
Nie możemy go tak zostawić.
If we take this any further, I'll become a murderer!
Jeśli posuniemy się dalej, stanę się mordercą!
That is not a person.
On nie jest człowiekiem.
I'm going to be killed by a human?
Zabije mnie człowiek?
Me?
Mnie?
It can't be.
Nie może tak być.
It makes no sense.
To nielogiczne.
It's over.
To koniec.
This body is useless now.
To ciało jest bezużyteczne.
I have to relocate.
Muszę się przenieść.
I don't know if it'll work, but…
Nie wiem, czy się uda, ale…
Tamiya Ryoko.
Tamiya Ryoko.
I will share her host.
Podzieli się ze mną gospodarzem.
Where is she?
Gdzie ona jest?
The police are here!
Przyjechała policja!
Five more meters.
Jeszcze pięć metrów.
OXYGEN
TLEN
KILLER INVADES HIGH SCHOOL
ZABÓJCA W SZKOLE
How is Shinichi?
- Jak się czuje Shinichi? - Nadal leży w łóżku.
Well, I'm just glad he wasn't hurt.
Dobrze, że nic mu się nie stało.
I can still remember what it felt like to stab him.
Ciągle pamiętam, jak go dźgnąłem.
As time passed and life settled down again,
Czas minął i życie wróciło do normy.
the school reopened and classes resumed.
Szkoła się otworzyła i wznowiono lekcje.
Tamiya Ryoko, who most likely killed A,
Tamiya Ryoko, która prawdopodobnie zabiła X,
continues to teach as though nothing's changed.
nadal uczy, jakby nic się nie stało.
I haven't heard any reports of murders in her vicinity,
Nie słyszałem o zabójstwach osób z jej otoczenia,
but she must still be killing.
ale ona pewnie nadal zabija.
We can't just let her keep doing whatever she wants.
Nie możemy pozwolić, żeby robiła, co chce.
STAFF CONFERENCE ROOM
POKÓJ NAUCZYCIELSKI
Well, how should I put this?
Jak to powiedzieć?
Tamiya-sensei.
Tamiya-sensei.
Regarding the fact that you are expecting,
Jest pani w ciąży.
while that is a joyous occasion in itself,
To radosna nowina,
you're a teacher!
ale jest pani nauczycielką!
And you're unmarried,
Nie ma pani męża
and you can't even say who the father is?
i nie wie, kim jest ojciec?
I hope it's not that you don't know who the father is
Mam nadzieję, że wie pani, kim on jest,
rather than being unable to tell us.
tylko nie chce nam powiedzieć.
This was unexpected.
To nie było planowane.
I didn't think it would end this way.
Nie wiedziałam, że tak to się skończy.
I don't want to attract attention over something like this.
Nie chcę skupiać na sobie uwagi przez takie coś.
I'm done being Tamiya Ryoko.
Nie chcę być Tamiyą Ryoko.
Wait, Tamiya-sensei.
Chwila, Tamiya-sensei!
Let's kill Tamiya Ryoko.
Zabijmy Tamiyę Ryoko.
I doubt we can win.
Wątpię, że wygramy.
Besides, the child within her is undeniably a human.
Poza tym nosi w sobie ludzkie dziecko.
Would you be able to kill that baby?
Zabijesz dziecko?
Tamiya Ryoko is no more.
Tamiyi Ryoko już nie ma.
Now, there is no particular reason to keep the humans around me,
Nie muszę już oszczędzać ludzi z mojego otoczenia.
including you, alive.
Ani ciebie.
Why do you kill people?
Dlaczego zabijasz ludzi?
My right hand is being kept alive by my blood.
Prawa ręka żyje dzięki mojej krwi.
That means it's surviving on normal food for humans.
Żywi się tym, czym ludzie.
Shouldn't the rest of you be able to live without eating humans, too?
Nie możecie żyć bez zabijania ludzi?
It's possible, I suppose.
Chyba możemy.
Then…
No to…
Flies know how to fly without being taught.
Muchy latają, a nikt ich tego nie uczy.
Spiders know how to spin webs
Pająki chodzą po pajęczynie, a nikt ich tego nie uczy.
Why is that?
Dlaczego?
That's…
No bo…
Here's what I think.
Myślę, że jest tak.
Flies and spiders are simply following a directive.
Muchy i pająki żyją według wytycznych.
I believe all life on Earth has received a directive of some kind.
Wszystkie istoty na ziemi dostały jakieś wytyczne.
What are you talking about?
O czym ty mówisz?
Do you get it?
Rozumiesz ją?
So humans have no directive?
Ludzie nie dostali wytycznych?
Like I said, what are you talking about?
O czym ty mówisz?
You mean, like, from a god?
Wytyczne od Boga?
When I took over this human's brain,
Gdy przejęłam mózg tej kobiety,
I received a directive.
dostałam wytyczne.
It said, "Devour this species."
„Pożryj ten gatunek”.
Tell me one thing.
Powiedz mi jedno.
The child you're carrying, what will you do with it?
Co zrobisz ze swoim dzieckiem?
I'll give birth to it.
Urodzę je.
I'm sure I can use it in some experiment.
Wykorzystam je do eksperymentu.
If I have no use for it, I'll eat it.
Jeśli będzie zbędne, zjem je.
Calm down, Shinichi!
Spokojnie, Shinichi!
We should not engage at this distance.
Jesteśmy za blisko.
You're getting on my nerves.
Wkurzasz mnie.
Die.
Umrzyj.
Shit!
Cholera!
As I thought, she has at least two morph patterns.
Ma co najmniej dwa wzory przemiany.
Not good.
Niedobrze.
Although it's minimal, you're no longer pure.
To minimalne, ale nie jesteś już czysty.
Interesting.
Ciekawe.
I won't kill you, after all.
Nie zabiję cię.
Hey!
Hej!
Ryoko!
Ryoko!
What's going on with you?
Co się z tobą dzieje?
I got a call from your school, so I rushed over!
Dzwonili ze szkoły, więc tu przyszłam.
She must be Tamiya Ryoko's mother.
To pewnie matka Tamiyi Ryoko.
Sorry, but I have somewhere I need to be.
Przepraszam, muszę coś załatwić.
Can we talk about this later?
Porozmawiamy później?
Ryoko.
Ryoko.
It's nearby, so I'll be back soon.
To blisko, zaraz wrócę.
Wait!
Czekaj!
Turn around!
Odwróć się!
Who…
Kim…
Who are you?
Kim jesteś?
It… It can't be.
To niemożliwe.
No!
Nie!
Ryoko.
Gdzie jest Ryoko?
Where is she?
Gdzie ona jest? Co z nią zrobiłaś?
Oh, no! I have to call the police!
O nie! Wezwę policję!
She saw through me in mere moments.
W jednej chwili mnie przejrzała.
My face and voice should be practically indistinguishable from Tamiya Ryoko, yet…
Mój głos i twarz są takie same jak Tamiyi Ryoko, a jednak…
I don't understand.
Nie rozumiem.
I doubt this woman had any special ability, but…
Wątpię, że ta kobieta miała jakieś zdolności, ale…
Migi?
Migi?
Don't scare me, Shinichi.
Nie strasz mnie!
What? You…
Co? Ty…
What's the matter? Why did you yell?
O co chodzi? Dlaczego krzyczysz?
Oh… A dream! I had a dream!
Coś mi się przyśniło!
Man, it was horrible.
Miałem straszny koszmar.
Go splash some water on your face.
Obmyj twarz wodą.
What are you doing?
Co robisz?
Well, at most, it's only three minutes that I can separate from you.
Mogę się od ciebie oddzielić co najwyżej na trzy minuty.
What was that? A morning walk?
Co to było? Poranny spacer?
Not a walk.
Nie spacer, tylko sprawdzian mobilności.
Mobility?
Mobilności?
Wait a minute. Are you going to take over my head?
Chwila. Chcesz przejąć mój mózg?
I told you I can't do that.
Mówiłem, że nie mogę.
Now that I've matured without eating a brain,
Dojrzałem, nie zjadając mózgu, więc nie wiem, jak kontrolować całe ciało.
But perhaps I should give it a try, regardless?
Ale może i tak spróbuję?
I was just joking.
Żartowałem.
Hey, hang on.
Chwila.
So those of you who've taken over the brain
Ci, którzy przejęli mózg,
can technically swap heads?
mogą zamieniać się głowami?
In theory, yes.
Tak, w teorii.
But there can be rejection,
Ale mogą spotkać się z odmową.
and besides, swapping heads is too dangerous.
Poza tym to zbyt niebezpieczne.
I doubt anyone would bother.
Wątpię, że ktoś zechce to zrobić.
A trip?
Wycieczka?
Yeah, I can finally take some time off.
Tak, w końcu dostałem urlop.
You'll be holding down the fort for a while.
Popilnujesz domu.
Your father's such a workaholic.
Twój tata to pracoholik.
We've barely gone on any trips together.
Rzadko razem wyjeżdżamy.
But isn't that risky?
To nie jest ryzykowne?
You mean because of the Mincemeat Murders?
Przez morderstwa zmielonego mięsa?
There haven't been as many recently,
Ostatnio ucichły. Nie mamy się czym martwić.
That's just what it looks like on the surface.
Może się tak wydawać.
Why wander around somewhere you've never been in times like these?
Po co chodzić po obcych okolicach w takich czasach?
Are you against it?
Mamy nie wyjeżdżać?
Yeah.
Tak.
even though you're in 12th grade.
Jesteś w 12. klasie.
That's not it!
Nie o to chodzi!
That's not the reason! It's that they…
To nie dlatego. Oni…
"They"?
„Oni”?
Never mind.
Nieważne.
Shinichi, if you're really against it, we can cancel.
Jeśli naprawdę nie chcesz, to nie pojedziemy.
Come now, honey.
Kochanie.
But there's something that's been bothering me for a while.
Od dłuższego czasu coś nie daje mi spokoju.
Is there something troubling you?
Masz jakieś problemy?
No, nothing really.
Nie mam.
One of your friends, maybe? Or…
Może chodzi o kolegę? Albo…
There's nothing, okay?
O nic nie chodzi.
I have to go to school.
Idę do szkoły.
Shinichi. I shouldn't need to remind you, but…
Shinichi, powinieneś o tym pamiętać, ale…
I know.
Wiem.
If I told my parents about my right hand,
Jeśli powiem rodzicom o prawej ręce,
there's no telling what Migi might do.
nie wiem, co zrobi Migi.
He only tries to protect me because I am his lifeline.
Chroni mnie, bo dzięki mnie żyje.
But my parents are a different story.
Moi rodzice to co innego.
He'll get rid of them without a moment's hesitation.
Bez wahania się ich pozbędzie.
Migi is not capable of affection.
Migi nie jest zdolny do uczuć.
When it comes down to it,
Tak naprawdę
Migi is no different from A or Tamiya Ryoko.
nie różni się od X czy Tamiyi Ryoko.
He's hiding something.
Coś ukrywa.
Of course he is.
To oczywiste.
He's in 12th grade.
Jest w 12. klasie.
It would only be natural for him to be keeping a few secrets from us.
To naturalne, że ma przed nami tajemnice.
Hell, I'd say he's been too good of a kid until now.
Muszę przyznać, że wcześniej był za grzeczny.
He didn't even really have a rebellious phase.
Nie buntował się.
Really?
Nie?
It could be because of that scar, actually.
Może przez tę bliznę.
What? Surely not.
Co? Na pewno nie.
That was so long ago.
To było dawno temu.
Hey, Mom! Give me a silver plate!
Mamo! Daj mi srebrny talerz!
Silver plate?
Srebrny talerz?
I'm going to use it for a science experiment in class tomorrow!
Wykorzystam go do eksperymentu w szkole.
Oh, by silver, you mean the aluminum foil plates?
Chodzi ci o aluminiowy talerz?
Yeah, those!
Tak!
Well, they're up on top of that,
Są wysoko na półce.
but I'm making tempura right now,
Teraz smażę tempurę.
-so wait until I'm done-- -I can get it!
- Poczekaj… - Wezmę je!
Hang on, Shinichi.
Ostrożnie, Shinichi.
Watch out!
Uważaj!
Ouch!
Boli!
Are you all right, Shinichi? Did any oil get on you?
Nic ci nie jest? Nie oblał cię olej?
Nothing hot hit you?
Uderzyło cię coś gorącego? Poparzyłeś się?
No.
Nie.
Nobuko, your hand.
- Nobuko, twoja ręka. - Co?
Ouch.
To bolało.
Your mom's hurting more.
Twoją mamę boli bardziej.
Huh? So I shouldn't be that worried?
Co? Nie powinienem się martwić?
Yes. Consider the probability.
Nie. Bo pomyśl tak.
My kind tends to congregate in urban areas where food is plentiful.
Mój gatunek gromadzi się w miastach, gdzie jest dużo jedzenia.
Not to mention, they tend to target solitary individuals.
Poza tym atakuje pojedyncze osoby.
If the two of them are taking a trip to the countryside,
Na wsi dwie osoby będą bezpieczniejsze niż tutaj.
I see.
Rozumiem.
Then I guess I shouldn't have been so against it.
Więc nie powinienem im zabraniać.
Shinichi.
Shinichi.
What?
Słucham?
Were you talking to someone just now?
Z kim rozmawiasz?
Just to myself! What did you need, anyway?
Ze sobą! Po co przyszłaś?
Well, dinner's almost ready.
Kolacja jest już prawie gotowa.
Oh, okay.
Dobrze.
I'll be down in a bit.
Zaraz przyjdę.
Oh, and Mom?
Mamo.
Please knock before you open the door next time!
Następnym razem pukaj, zanim wejdziesz!
Don't forget, okay?
Pamiętaj o tym, dobrze?
Okay.
Dobrze.
Excuse me.
Przepraszam.
I thought I was going to have a heart attack.
Myślałem, że dostanę zawału.
A heart attack?
Zawału?
That would be inconvenient.
To byłby kłopot.
Shinichi yelled at me.
Shinichi mnie okrzyczał.
What? Was he spanking the monkey or something?
Co? Czochrał freda czy co?
I said this morning that I was against your trip,
Rano byłem przeciwny waszej wycieczce, ale zmieniłem zdanie.
I think it's good to get away from the crowd sometimes
Dobrze uciec od tłumu
and go relax somewhere with fresh air.
i odprężyć się na łonie natury.
So, when do you leave?
Kiedy wyjeżdżacie?
-I don't get it. -Huh?
Nie rozumiem.
I don't get you, Shinichi.
Nie rozumiem cię, Shinichi.
What's going on with you?
Co się z tobą dzieje?
You were so against it this morning.
Rano byłeś przeciwny.
What was that about?
Dlaczego?
And now, you've done a total 180!
A teraz się zgadzasz?
So now, you don't even care about your parents?
Nie obchodzą cię twoi rodzice?
That's not true.
Obchodzicie mnie!
Mom, what's up with you?
Mamo, co ty wygadujesz?
I just don't get it.
Nie rozumiem.
I don't get what's going on with you!
Nie wiem, co się z tobą dzieje!
Something's… Something's changed.
Coś się zmieniło.
It's like…
To jakby…
It's like you're not my son.
Jakbyś nie był moim synem.
Nobuko.
Nobuko.
Please tell me!
Powiedz mi!
What's happened to you?
Co się z tobą stało?
Shinichi.
Shinichi.
I thought I'd be lonely.
Myślałem, że będę samotny.
At least, I did this morning.
Rano tak myślałem.
But when I talked to my friends about it, they laughed at me.
Ale powiedziałem o tym kolegom i mnie wyśmiali.
So I thought things over.
Więc to przemyślałem.
That's why I'm fine now.
Dlatego teraz się zgadzam.
If I get lonely, I can just invite a friend over.
Jeśli będę samotny, zaproszę kolegę.
That's really all it was.
Tylko o to mi chodziło.
That's enough, right?
Już wystarczy, prawda?
They said it'd be a while before the taxi arrives.
Musicie poczekać na taksówkę.
You know, this might be the first time we've been gone for so long.
Pierwszy raz wyjeżdżamy na tak długo.
Back when we lived in an apartment, we didn't have that luxury.
Gdy mieszkaliśmy w mieszkaniu, nie było nas na to stać.
Things were tough back then.
Było nam ciężko.
Come to think of it, I also got this burn back then.
Wtedy też się oparzyłam.
All right, take care.
Dobra. Trzymaj się.
Oh, I will!
Dobrze!
Don't forget to turn off the stove and lock the door.
Wyłączaj kuchenkę i zamykaj drzwi.
Right.
Dobrze.
And don't worry about us.
Nie martw się o nas.
See you!
Do zobaczenia!
It moved.
Ruszyło się.
Next time, "The Stranger."
Następny odcinek: „Nieznajomy”.